Guide to the Adolph Burnett Benson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Adolph Burnett Benson papers
1920-1961
MS 76
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(16 boxes)
University professor and writer, Correspondence, writings, photographs, clippings and teaching materials largely related to Benson's career at Yale University and his work in connection with the American-Swedish community. Included in the papers is the unfinished draft of a book, Americans from Sweden, as well as articles on literary subjects.
Benson, Adolph B. (Adolph Burnett), 1881-1962
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Adolph Benson in 1960 and of Mrs. Benson in 1963.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings and Miscellany.
Scope and Contents
The Adolph B. Benson Papers consist of seven linear feet of correspondence, writings, photographs, clippings, and teaching material spanning Benson's entire academic career. They are arranged in two series, CORRESPONDENCE and WRITINGS AND MISCELLANY. Most of the letters were written in these years: 1920-1934, 1946-1961. They are related mainly to Benson's teaching and publications, to his work on behalf of the American-Swedish Historical Foundation and the American-Scandinavian Foundation and to family matters. The writings are drafts of Americans from Sweden (incomplete) and of articles and essays on literary subjects. The photographs are of several unidentified persons (one of whom may be the young Adolph Benson) and of book exhibits by the Swedish American Line. The teaching material consists of lecture notes from Benson's years at Columbia and gradebooks spanning most of his career at Yale.
The Benson Papers were given to Yale University Library by Professor Benson in 1960 and by Mrs. Benson in 1963.
Biographical / Historical
Taught at Columbia University, 1909-1911, at Dartmouth, 1911-1914, and at Sheffield Scientific School, 1914-1920; professor of German and Scandinavian at Yale University, 1920-1947; chairman of Department of Germanic Languages, 1932-1944.
Emigration and immigration; Literature -- History and criticism; Swedes -- United States; Authors; Educators; Historians; Benson, Adolph B. (Adolph Burnett), 1881-1962; American Swedish Historical Foundation, Philadelphia; American-Scandinavian Foundation; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Germanic Languages
- Correspondence, 1911-1962; Series I; 4' (10 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The arrangement is chronological.
  - 1911 March 3-1919 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - August 9-November 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1919 December 2-1920 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - February 3-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1920 March 3-April 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1920 April 13-July 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1920 July 11-October 19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1920 October 24-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [1920?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1921 January 13-May 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1921 May 14-August 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1921 August 15-October 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1921 November 1-December 26 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [1921?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1922 January 1-February 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1922 February 10-April 7 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1922 April 11-May 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1920 May 20-December 30 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1922 October 31-December 30 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - [1922?] (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1923 January 2-25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1923 January 30-February 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1923 March 1-18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1923 March 21-April 30 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1923 May 2-June 13 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1923 June 16-September 25 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1923 September 26-November 19 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1923 November 20-December 22 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - [1923?] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1924 January 8-28 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1924 January 29-February 28 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1924 March 4-May 28 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 1924 June 1-September 1 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 1924 September 8-November 12 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 1924 November 13-December 31 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - [1924?] (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1925 January 5-February 13 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 1925 February 17-April 18 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - 1925 April 22-June 17 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - 1925 July 8-August 15 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - 1925 August 17-September 16 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - 1925 September 17-October 29 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - 1925 November 1-December 9 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 1925 December 10-1926 January 26 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - 1926 January 28-February 17 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - 1926 February 20-March 28 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - 1926 March 30-May 10 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - 1926 May 11-29 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - 1926 June 1-14 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - 1926 June 16-July 27 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - 1926 July 28-November 22 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - [1926?] (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - 1927 February 2-1929 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - [1920s?] (Box 2, Folder 54-58)
  - 1930 January 21-October 23 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - 1930 October 24-Nove 20 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - 1930 November 22-December 28 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - 1931 January 1-February 6 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - 1931 February 9-March 13 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - 1931 March 16-April 26 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - 1931 April 28-May 19 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - 1931 May 31-June 23 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - 1931 July 16-September 16 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - 1931 September 31-November 2 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - 1931 November 3-December 27 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - [1930-1932?] (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - 1933 January 5-November 20 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - 1934 September 12-1940 July 29 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - 1940 July 31-August 26 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - 1940 August 28-1941 August 11 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - 1941 August 14-1944 October 18 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - 1944 November 15-1945 September 18 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - 1945 October 1-December 6 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - 1946 January 24-November 6 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - 1946 November 21-December 16 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - 1946 December 18-28 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - [1946?] (Box 3, Folder 81-82)
  - 1947 January 2- 21 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - 1947 January 23-February 18 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - 1947 February 19-March 14 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - 1947 March 22-April 30 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - 1947 May 1-16 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - 1947 May 17-June 12 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - 1947 June 15-July 28 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - 1947 July 29-September 2 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - 1947 September 3-October 17 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - 1947 October 21-November 17 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - 1947 November 18-December 3 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - 1947 December 4-December 29 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - 1947 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - [1947?] (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - 1948 January 2-January 20 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - 1948 January 21-February 18 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - 1948 February 19-March 18 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - 1948 March 19-April 18 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - 1948 April 20-May 26 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - 1948 May 27-June 29 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - 1948 July 2-July 27 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - 1948 July 28-August 31 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - 1948 September 2-October 15 (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - 1948 October 19-November 13 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - 1948 November 15-30 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - 1948 December 1-11 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - 1948 December 12-30 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - [1948?] (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - 1949 January 3-20 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - 1949 January 21-February 2 (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - 1948 February 4-16 (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - 1949 February 17-March 7 (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - 1949 March 8-18 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - 1949 March 20-April 8 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - 1949 April 10-May 9 (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - 1949 May 11-June 1 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - 1949 June 7-29 (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - 1949 July 6-August 8 (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - 1949 August 11- September 22 (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - 1949 September 23-November 3 (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - 1949 November 4-21 (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - 1949 November 22-December 13 (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - 1949 December 15-30 (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - [1948-1949] (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - [1949?] (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - 1950 January 2-21 (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - 1950 January 25-February 2 (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - 1950 February 3-21 (Box 5, Folder 130)
  - 1950 February 23-March 23 (Box 5, Folder 131)
  - 1950 March 24-31 (Box 5, Folder 132)
  - 1950 April 1-29 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - 1950 May 2-31 (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - 1950 June 1-29 (Box 6, Folder 135)
  - 1950 July 4-August 14 (Box 6, Folder 136)
  - 1950 August 15-September 8 (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - 1950 September 14-October 9 (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - 1950 October 10-November 10 (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - 1950 November 12-24 (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - 1950 November 25-December 8 (Box 6, Folder 141)
  - 1950 December 10-31 (Box 6, Folder 142)
  - [1950?] (Box 6, Folder 143-144)
  - 1951 January 3-February 5 (Box 6, Folder 145)
  - 1951 February 8-27 (Box 6, Folder 146)
  - 1951 February 28-March 14 (Box 6, Folder 147)
  - 1951 March 15-26 (Box 6, Folder 148)
  - 1951 March 27-April 3 (Box 6, Folder 149)
  - 1951 April 4-16 (Box 6, Folder 150)
  - 1951 April 17-30 (Box 6, Folder 151)
  - 1951 May 1-18 (Box 6, Folder 152)
  - 1951 May 19-July 3 (Box 6, Folder 153)
  - 1951 July 5-23 (Box 6, Folder 154)
  - 1951 July 24-August 13 (Box 6, Folder 155)
  - 1951 August 15-September 12 (Box 6, Folder 156)
  - 1951 September 14-October 16 (Box 6, Folder 157)
  - 1951 October 19-November 20 (Box 6, Folder 158)
  - 1951 November 21-22 (Box 6, Folder 159)
  - 1951 November 26-December 27 (Box 7, Folder 160)
  - [1951?] (Box 7, Folder 161)
  - 1952 January 2-16 (Box 7, Folder 162)
  - 1952 January 19-31 (Box 7, Folder 163)
  - 1952 February 1-13 (Box 7, Folder 164)
  - 1952 February 14-25 (Box 7, Folder 165)
  - 1952 February 26-March 15 (Box 7, Folder 166)
  - 1952 March 16-31 (Box 7, Folder 167)
  - 1952 April 1-8 (Box 7, Folder 168)
  - 1952 April 9-26 (Box 7, Folder 169)
  - 1952 April 27-May 6 (Box 7, Folder 170)
  - 1952 May 7-June 8 (Box 7, Folder 171)
  - 1952 June 13-30 (Box 7, Folder 172)
  - 1952 July 4-9 (Box 7, Folder 173)
  - 1952 July 17-August 11 (Box 7, Folder 174)
  - 1952 August 12-September 10 (Box 7, Folder 175)
  - 1952 September 11-26 (Box 7, Folder 176)
  - 1952 September 29-October 28 (Box 7, Folder 177)
  - 1952 October 29-November 18 (Box 7, Folder 178)
  - 1952 November 19-December 4 (Box 7, Folder 179)
  - 1952 December 5-18 (Box 7, Folder 180)
  - 1952 December 20-31 (Box 7, Folder 181)
  - 1953 January 2-21 (Box 7, Folder 182)
  - 1953 January 24-February 28 (Box 7, Folder 183)
  - 1953 March 2-28 (Box 7, Folder 184)
  - 1953 March 30-April 13 (Box 7, Folder 185)
  - 1953 April 14-27 (Box 7, Folder 186)
  - 1953 April 28-May 1 (Box 7, Folder 187)
  - 1953 May 3-17 (Box 7, Folder 188)
  - 1953 May 18-August 12 (Box 7, Folder 189)
  - 1953 August 13-December 23 (Box 7, Folder 190)
  - [1953?] (Box 8, Folder 191)
  - 1954 May 15-December 20 (Box 8, Folder 192)
  - [1954?] (Box 8, Folder 193)
  - 1955 January 11-February 23 (Box 8, Folder 194)
  - 1955 February 24-April 5 (Box 8, Folder 195)
  - 1955 April 15-May 20 (Box 8, Folder 196)
  - 1955 May 21-June 17 (Box 8, Folder 197)
  - 1955 June 22-July 20 (Box 8, Folder 198)
  - 1955 July 22-September 23 (Box 8, Folder 199)
  - 1955 October 3-November 12 (Box 8, Folder 200)
  - 1955 November 17-December 20 (Box 8, Folder 201)
  - [1955?] (Box 8, Folder 202)
  - 1956 January 2-February 25 (Box 8, Folder 203)
  - 1956 February 26-March 1 (Box 8, Folder 204)
  - 1956 March 2-April 8 (Box 8, Folder 205)
  - 1956 April 9-30 (Box 8, Folder 206)
  - 1956 May 2-June 17 (Box 8, Folder 207)
  - 1956 June 20-September 20 (Box 8, Folder 208)
  - 1956 September 24-October 31 (Box 8, Folder 209)
  - 1956 November 2-27 (Box 8, Folder 210)
  - 1956 November 28-December 30 (Box 8, Folder 211)
  - [1956?] (Box 8, Folder 212)
  - 1957 January 2-19 (Box 8, Folder 213)
  - 1957 January 22-February 11 (Box 8, Folder 214)
  - 1957 February 13-25 (Box 8, Folder 215)
  - 1957 March 2-April 15 (Box 8, Folder 216)
  - 1957 April 17-May 10 (Box 8, Folder 217)
  - 1957 May 13-June 1 (Box 8, Folder 218)
  - 1957 June 2-18 (Box 9, Folder 219)
  - 1957 June 19-28 (Box 9, Folder 220)
  - 1957 July 1-29 (Box 9, Folder 221)
  - 1957 August 1-September 11 (Box 9, Folder 222)
  - 1957 September 12-27 (Box 9, Folder 223)
  - 1957 September 28-October 28 (Box 9, Folder 224)
  - 1957 October 30-November 11 (Box 9, Folder 225)
  - 1957 November 12-25 (Box 9, Folder 226)
  - 1957 November 27-December 21 (Box 9, Folder 227)
  - [1957?] (Box 9, Folder 228)
  - 1958 January 3-February 27 (Box 9, Folder 229)
  - 1958 March 2-27 (Box 9, Folder 230)
  - 1958 April 1-30 (Box 9, Folder 231)
  - 1958 May 8-June 7 (Box 9, Folder 232)
  - 1958 June 9-July 7 (Box 9, Folder 233)
  - 1958 July 18-September 2 (Box 9, Folder 234)
  - 1958 September 3-October 27 (Box 9, Folder 235)
  - 1958 November 2-December 31 (Box 9, Folder 236)
  - [1958?] (Box 9, Folder 237)
  - 1959 January 2-22 (Box 9, Folder 238)
  - 1959 January 25-February 23 (Box 9, Folder 239)
  - 1959 February 24-April 21 (Box 9, Folder 240)
  - 1959 April 22-May 5 (Box 9, Folder 241)
  - 1959 May 9-June 15 (Box 9, Folder 242)
  - 1959 June 23-July 16 (Box 9, Folder 243)
  - 1959 July 18-August 21 (Box 9, Folder 244)
  - 1959 August 23-September 30 (Box 9, Folder 245)
  - 1959 October 1-9 (Box 9, Folder 246)
  - 1959 October 19-December 29 (Box 9, Folder 247)
  - [1959?] (Box 9, Folder 248)
  - 1960 January 7-February 14 (Box 10, Folder 249)
  - 1960 February 15-March 9 (Box 10, Folder 250)
  - 1960 March 10-April 20 (Box 10, Folder 251)
  - 1960 April 22-June 4 (Box 10, Folder 252)
  - 1960 June 6-23 (Box 10, Folder 253)
  - 1960 June 28-October 31 (Box 10, Folder 254)
  - 1960 November 4-December 31 (Box 10, Folder 255)
  - [1960?] (Box 10, Folder 256)
  - 1961 January 10-March 16 (Box 10, Folder 257)
  - 1961 March 18-May 4 (Box 10, Folder 258)
  - 1961 May 8-June 7 (Box 10, Folder 259)
  - 1961 June 9-August 7 (Box 10, Folder 260)
  - 1961 August 8-October 11 (Box 10, Folder 261)
  - 1961 October 16-November 15 (Box 10, Folder 262)
  - 1961 November 20-22 (Box 10, Folder 263)
  - 1961 November 27-December 30 (Box 10, Folder 264)
  - [1961?] (Box 10, Folder 265)
  - 1962 January 4-29 (Box 10, Folder 266)
- Writings and Miscellany, 1907-1950, undated; Series II; 3' (6 boxes)
  The papers are in the order: clippings, articles and essays, miscellaneous papers, photographs, Americans from Sweden, lecture notes, and gradebooks.
  - Clippings, 1903, 1916, 1917, 1918, 1920-1962 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
  - "The Origin of the Nibelungensaga, up to its Epic Form, the 'Nibelungenlied'" (Thesis presented for Special Honors in German, Wesleyan University), 1907 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - "The Legend and Development of 'Tristan and Iseult'", 1907 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "Hermann's Battle in the German Drama" (M.A. thesis, Columbia University), 1910 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "Sweden and the American Revolution", 1925 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "A week on Block Island, 1931" (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Letter to the editor of the Providence Journal, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - "The Number of English Translations of Frithiofs Saga ", undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "The Problem of Catholic Sympathies in Swedish Romanticism", undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - "Scholars in Scandinavian Studies Meet at Upsala College", undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - "Strindberg", undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - "Swedish Literature", undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - " Swedish literature from 1830 to 1870...", undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Svenskarnas väg österut och söderut, undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Notes on language, undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Addresses saved by Benson, undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Resumés of persons other than Benson, undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous papers re: the American-Swedish Historical Museum and the American-Swedish Historical Foundation, undated (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter, undated (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Americans from Sweden
    - Introduction, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - Chapter I, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Chapter III, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - [Chapter IV?], 1949 (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - Chapter VII, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 34)
    - Chapter XI, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 35)
    - Chapter XII, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 36)
    - Chapter XIII, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 37)
    - Chapter XIV, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 38)
    - Chapter XVI, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 39)
    - [Chapter XVII?], 1949 (Box 13, Folder 40)
    - Chapter XVIII, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 41)
    - Chapter XIX, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 42)
    - Chapter XX, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 43)
    - Chapter XXII, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 44)
    - Chapter XXIII, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 45)
    - [Chapter XXX?], 1949 (Box 13, Folder 46)
    - Bibliography, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 47)
  - Lecture notebooks, 1909-1911 (Box 14)
  - Lecture notebooks, 1909-1911 (Box 15)
  - Gradebooks, 1916-1950 (Box 16)